PAVAN BALOJU

- pavanbaloju9@gmail.com
- linkedin.com/in/pavanbaloju
- pavanbaloju.github.io
- +91 7732006410

SUMMARY

Full stack developer with experience of 1.5 years. I am an active follower of TDD and clean code and ensure to deliver with quality. I worked in the e-com domain so far and looking to work where I can use my skills to best, add value to the team and grow as a professional

EDUCATION

B. Tech - RGUKT, Basar [07/2017 – 05/2021]

• Graduate in CSE with a CGPA of 8.91

COMPETENCIES

- Java Spring Boot, React, Node, HTML, JavaScript
- SQL, NoSQL, HBase, Mapreduce, Cosmos DB., Document storage, Postgres
- OOPS, TDD, Junit, Design patterns
- Kafka, Docker, Confluent, SCDF, Vault
- C, C++, Python, Java, Data Structures, Algorithms
- Machine Learning, Deep Learning, CNN, Keras, TensorFlow

CERTIFICATIONS

- The Complete Web Developer in 2023 Udemy
- Machine Learning by Andrew Ng
- Deep Learning Specialization by Andrew Ng

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Secured a rank of 673 in TCS Codevita Season 9 out of 16K rankings
- Topped my Mandal in SSC with a CGPA of 10 in 2015
- Football championship in university sports events in 2017
- Business Debate Champions in university technical fest in 2020

WORK HISTORY

Application Developer - Thoughtworks, Hyderabad

[08/2021 to Present]

- Developed POCs for integrating azure blob storage and cosmos db with Spring Boot to design an architecture that minimizes cloud expenses
- Implemented Spring Kafka for real-time publishing/consuming of data changes replacing the legacy way of delayed updates
- Improved performance of map-reduce jobs on HBase for data extraction by configuring reducers and bringing down the job execution time from 60mins to 20mins
- Implemented Circuit Breaker to make the application resilient to Kafka failures and prevent data loss
- Identified logging optimization techniques to save Splunk expenses
- Demonstrated TDD and clean code in the team to improve the code coverage and deliver bug-free products

Application Developer Intern - Thoughtworks, Hyderabad [04/2021 to 07/2021]

- Built micro service starter kits in Java spring boot and Golang, for developer communities to save time and effort of Iteration-0 for green field projects
- Implemented sensible defaults following best practices which are easy to enable/disable and added quick setup guides. Developers will now have a base project ready to add business logic specific to projects.
- 20 client projects have used these starter kits and stated they saved the effort of 2 dev pairs for at least 2 weeks

Summer Research Intern - IIT Kharagpur, Remote [06/2020 to 07/2020]

- Performed semantic segmentation of agriculture-vision dataset of 1200 images by applying deep learning models to annotate pixels as a green cover or barren land
- Used combinations of Resnet50, U-net and EfficientNet encoder-decoder architectures applied optimization techniques and recorded results
- Achieved classification accuracy of 0.86 which is very close to the state-of-theart models

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Smart Brain - Web application integrated with face detection

- Developed the interface using React where users can provide an image URL and detect a face in the given image
- Introduced sign-up and sign-in features for user authentication and user data is stored in a Postgres where the passwords are encrypted using bcrypt
- Developed the backend using Node and Express while the face detection is achieved by the Clarifai module

Lucy - Voice based windows GUI automation application

- Built the application using python for automating basic operations in windows using voice commands
- Voice commands would work with VLC, Camera, Notepad, YouTube, and Browser for which python modules like pyautogui, pyttsx3, and speech recognition were used